{"tossups": [{"question": "This person lobbied for the 1831 Copyright Act, the first major revision to American copyright law. This author once edited the Federalist newspaper <em>The American Minerva</em> and wanted to end American reliance on British school books. This man\u2019s \u201cblue-backed spellers\u201d were used to teach generations of young students to read and write. For ten points, name this man whose <em>American Dictionary of the English Language</em> was sold to the Merriam family after his death.", "answer": "<b><u>N</u></b>oah <b><u>Webster</u></b> (prompt on \u201cWebster\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city was the site of the 1966 Compton's Cafeteria Riot, which involved members of the Vanguard organization. Bill Kraus and Cleve Jones were activists in this city's Castro District. This city's mayor, George Moscone, was assassinated by Dan White, whose lawyers used the \"Twinkie Defense.\" The White Night riots occurred in this city following the assassination of Harvey Milk. For ten points, name this California center of LGBTQ activism, situated on a namesake bay.", "answer": "<b><u>San Francisco</u></b>, California", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Galen believed these people were dominated by blood humor and red choler, unlike others who had an excess of black choler or phlegm. These people play in the Scottish poem \"Rait's Raving.\u201d Only under Victorian law was the labor of these people restricted as, for much of history, these people were seen as simply smaller versions of adults. Canon law in medieval England stated this period in human development ended at age 12. For ten points, name this period before adolescence.", "answer": "<b><u>Children</u></b> (accept answers such as <b><u>Childhood</u></b> indicating the period of human development prior to adulthood)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "The oldest of these structures still in use, located in A Coru\u00f1a [[ah cor-OON-ya]], Spain, was built in the second century. An Oscar-nominated 2019 film directed by Robert Eggers is set in one of these places and stars Robert Pattinson and Willem Dafoe. The first of these built on the open ocean was built by Henry Winstanley at Eddystone Rocks. One of these buildings in Egypt was severely damaged by three earthquakes during the Middle Ages and was also known as the \u201cPharos.\u201d For ten points, name these towers that aid ships in navigation.", "answer": "<b><u>Lighthouse</u></b>s", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A UN-supervised referendum led to this country\u2019s formal independence in 1993, resulting in a nationalist one-party state. In 1994, then-US President Bill Clinton called this country\u2019s president, Isaias Afwerki, \u201ca renaissance African leader.\u201d Reporters Without Borders rates this country lowest in the world on its Press Freedom Index, and until 2018 this country was at war with Ethiopia. For ten points, name this East African country, whose capital is Asmara.", "answer": "State of <b><u>Eritrea</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Oprah Winfrey and this man are producing a series on mental health for Apple TV+, and this man launched an orphans' charity called <em>Sentebale</em>. The Taliban threatened to kidnap or kill this man while he was at Camp Bastion in Afghanistan. This man was once photographed at Highgrove House wearing an Afrika Korps uniform. With his wife, this man founded Archewell, Inc. for creative media ventures. The brother of Prince William and the son of Princess Diana, for ten points, name this prince who is married to Meghan Markle.", "answer": "Prince <b><u>Harry</u></b> (accept <b><u>Duke of Sussex</u></b>; accept <b><u>Henry</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The site of these clashes is marked by eleven \u201cwitness houses,\u201d as well as a stretch of Battle Road. A Daniel Chester French statue representing Captain Isaac Davis was unveiled at the centennial celebration of these battles. An annual reenactment staged by His Majesty\u2019s 10th Regiment of Foot, along with volunteer militias from local Massachusetts towns, commemorates, for ten points, what pair of 1775 battles, legendarily started with the \u201cshot heard \u2018round the world\u2019\u201d?", "answer": "Battles of <b><u>Lexington</u></b> and <b><u>Concord</u></b> (accept in any order)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A 1951 song about the \u201cBlack Strap\u201d type of this substance, performed by Groucho Marx and three others, extolled its supposed health benefits. One of George Washington\u2019s notebooks contains a recipe for \u201csmall beer\u201d made with this substance. A different beverage made from this liquid was supposedly invented in Nevis in the 17th century and was used to pay guards as part of the African slave trade. In 1919, 21 people were killed by a flood of, for ten points, what syrupy byproduct of sugar production, the principal ingredient in rum?", "answer": "<b><u>Molasses</u></b> (or <b><u>Black Treacle</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Actor Max von Sydow plays a medieval knight during this historical event who plays chess with Death in the Ingmar Bergman film, <em>The Seventh Seal</em>. Fiammetta tells a story of the king\u2019s inability to seduce a woman while on her first day of quarantine during this event. Ten men and women escaping this historical event tell 100 stories while hiding in a villa outside Florence in Boccaccio\u2019s <em>The Decameron</em>. For ten points, name this pandemic which killed one-third of Europe's population in the 14th century.", "answer": "The <b><u>Black Death</u></b> (accept Bubonic <b><u>Plague</u></b>; accept Black <b><u>Plague</u></b>; accept <b><u>Great</u></b> <b><u>Mortality</u></b>; accept the <b><u>Pestilence</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "Julio Cervera Baviera developed this technology in Spain, and Reginald Fessenden developed some of its early practical uses. In \"Surely You're Joking, Mr. Feynman,\u201d the young Feynman fixes these items in a hotel. Zenith sold these items, whose first commercial use was by KDKA in Pittsburgh. These items used vacuum tubes or worked in crystal sets, and the first of these items was created by Guglielmo Marconi after research on electromagnetic waves by Heinrich Hertz. For ten points, name this communications technology.", "answer": "<b><u>Radio</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "Sufi Abdul Hamid targeted Jews as well as people of this ethnicity. Governor John M. Parker organized an 1891 lynch mob against people of this ethnicity. Germans and prisoners of war of this ethnicity were housed at Camp Albuquerque. Joe Ettor organized these people in labor movements, and eleven men of this ethnicity were lynched in 1891 in New Orleans after Police Chief David Hennessy was murdered. Often Roman Catholic, for ten points, name this ethnicity that included people like Sacco and Vanzetti.", "answer": "<b><u>Italian</u></b>-American", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man's daughter Edda had an affair with a Chinese warlord, and his men fought Omar Mukhtar in the \"Pacification of Libya.\u201d To delay an annexation and war, this man participated in the Stresa Front. This man reclaimed land in the Battle for Land, and it was claimed that this man finally \"made trains run on time.\" In 1922, after the March on Rome, this man became the youngest Italian Prime Minister and signed the Lateran Treaty with the Vatican. For ten points, name this man who created the Rome-Berlin Axis with Adolf Hitler.", "answer": "Benito <b><u>Mussolini</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This woman was mentored by gospel singers Clara Ward and Mahalia Jackson after her mother died. This woman\u2019s first Top Ten pop hit, \u201cI Never Loved A Man (The Way I Love You)\u201d was recorded at FAME Studios in Muscle Shoals, and among her 16 other Top Ten hits in the US were \u201cThink\u201d and \u201cWho\u2019s Zoomin\u2019 Who.\u201d In 1987, this singer became the first woman inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame. \u201cChain of Fools\u201d and \u201c(You Make Me Feel) Like A Natural Woman\u201d are award-winning songs by, for ten points, what woman known as the Queen of Soul?", "answer": "Aretha <b><u>Franklin</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "Maurice Francis Egan tried to trade for this region in exchange for Mindanao. Expeditions to Sabine and Shannon Islands near this region were part of the North Atlantic weather war. Charles Francis Hall saw much of the northwest of this region, and its northern part was claimed by the <em>Polaris</em> expedition. Part of this island was claimed by Norway as \u201cErik the Red's Land,\u201d and Project Icework attempted to construct hundreds of minuteman missiles on this island. For ten points, name this large island within the Kingdom of Denmark.", "answer": "<b><u>Greenland</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "The first person to win this award was Dorothy P. Lathrop for her work titled <em>Animals of the Bible</em>. Barbara Cooney won this award twice, first for <em>Chanticleer and the Fox</em>, and then for <em>The Ox-Cart Man</em>. The first novel to be given this award was Brian Selznick\u2019s <em>The Invention of Hugo Cabret</em>, and the most recent winner of this award was <em>We Are Water</em> <em>Protectors</em> by Michaela Goade. <em>This is Not My Hat</em>, <em>Jumanji</em>, and <em>Where the Wild Things Are</em> have all received, for ten points, what award given for excellence in picture book illustration?", "answer": "<b><u>Caldecott</u></b> Medal", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "In this city, Roscoe Conkling Simmons worked as a columnist and politician. This city\u2019s second African-American alderman, Louis B. Anderson, succeeded the first, Oscar Stanton De Priest, who was defended from graft by Clarence Darrow. Robert S. Abbott started this city\u2019s Bud Billiken Parade and Picnic and founded the <em>Defender</em> newspaper. In 1993, this city's Hyde Park neighborhood supported Carol Moseley Braun for US senator.  For ten points, name this Midwest city where Barack Obama served as a voter organizer.", "answer": "<b><u>Chicago</u></b>, Illinois", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In this city in 2019, white-shirted mobsters attacked MTR passengers with steel rods until police arrived 39 minutes later. Relations between this city's residents and police worsened after an attack at Prince Edward subway station. In this city, protestors wore black while trying to \"be water\" per Bruce Lee's philosophy. This city faced 2019-20 protests over an extradition bill authored by the CCP. For ten points, name this Southern Chinese city governed by Carrie Lam, where protests broke out over Mainland China's control over civil liberties.", "answer": "<b><u>Hong Kong</u></b> Special Administrative Region of the People's Republic of China (accept <b><u>HKSAR</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Gaspar Fagel spread pamphlets supporting this event, and new French tariffs on herring imports led directly to its occurrence. This event led to the Age of the Projectors and an Act of Toleration to protect non-conformist Protestants. After this event, the Coronation Oath Act, the Declaration of Right, and a Bill of Rights were passed, which allowed for freedom of speech and free elections for Parliament. James II was deposed in favor of his daughter and her husband in, for ten points, what 1688 British regime change?", "answer": "<b><u>Glorious Revolution</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Founder of the American Red Cross.", "answer": "Clara <b><u>Barton</u> </b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Standard Oil tycoon who funded it.", "answer": "John D. <b><u>Rockefeller</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "US President, also a Supreme Court Chief Justice, who was Chairperson from 1915 to 1919.", "answer": "William Howard <b><u>Taft</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "2005 hurricane after which it raised more than $2 billion to aid the New Orleans area.", "answer": "<b><u>Katrina</u> </b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Earth Science"}, {"question": "Disease that crippled FDR against which president Basil O'Connor fought.", "answer": "<b><u>Polio</u></b>myelitis", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Company that sued the American Red Cross over their emblem.", "answer": "<b><u>Johnson & Johnson</u></b> (prompt on \"J&J\")", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Most destructive European earthquake that struck Reggio Calabria, after which it started international aid.", "answer": "1908 <b><u>Messina</u></b> earthquake", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Humanitarian village the American Red Cross created after the Battle of Caporetto.", "answer": "<b><u>Pisa</u></b> Village", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Battle which included a 26 mile run to Athens according to Herodotus.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Marathon</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Ruler whose founding of the first Persian Empire is recounted in Herodotus\u2019s <em>Histories</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Cyrus</u></b> II (accept <b><u>Cyrus</u></b> the Great; accept <b><u>Cyrus</u></b> the Elder)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "City Herodotus claimed to have visited, though he doesn't mention its Hanging Gardens.", "answer": "<b><u>Babylon</u> </b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "African mammal described as a hybrid of a camel and a leopard by Herodotus.", "answer": "<b><u>Giraffe</u> </b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "480 naval victory by Themistocles that crippled Xerxes\u2019s invasion of Greece.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Salamis</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Greco-Roman historian who wrote <em>On the Malice of Herodotus</em> and <em>Parallel Lives</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Plutarch</u> </b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "Wealthy Lydian king described by Herodotus as minting the first coins.", "answer": "<b><u>Croesus</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Spartan king whom Herodotus describes as burning his foes in the Sacred Grove of Argus.", "answer": "<b><u>Cleomenes</u></b> I", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "Desert that covered most of the northern parts of the AEF.", "answer": "<b><u>Sahara</u></b> Desert", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Religion of pre-colonial rulers who destroyed the <em>mune</em> and took a pilgrimage to Mecca.", "answer": "<b><u>Islam</u></b> (accept <b><u>Muslim</u></b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Government-in-exile led by Charles de Gaulle, joined by the AEF in opposition to the Vichy regime.", "answer": "<b><u>Free France</u></b> (accept <b><u>Free French</u></b> forces)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Republic of the Congo capital that held a Conference to increase colonial rights for natives.", "answer": "<b><u>Brazzaville</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Country David Dacko and Jean-B\u00e9del Bokassa governed from Bangui.", "answer": "<b><u>Central African Republic</u></b> (or <b><u>CAR</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Constituent country that F\u00e9lix Malloum and Hissene Habr\u00e9 led.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Chad</u> </b>  Strip of land that Libya tried to take in the Toyota War. (7)  ANSWER: <b><u>Aouzou</u></b> Strip", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Black French administrator, earlier governor of Guadeloupe, who had his ashes placed in the Panth\u00e9on.", "answer": "F\u00e9lix <b><u>\u00c9bou\u00e9</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This amendment has never been the primary basis of a Supreme Court</u></b> <b><u>decision and wasn\u2019t even interpreted by a US court until 1982\u2019s</u> </b><em><b><u>Engblom v. Carey</u></b></em><b><u>.</u></b> <b><u>Justice William O. Douglas used this amendment, along with other parts of the (*)</u> Bill of Rights, as part of the decision in </b><em><b>Griswold v. Connecticut</b></em><b> as an example of freedom from undue influence by the state. Proposed in 1789 in opposition to laws regarding the (*) </b>British army, for ten points, name this Constitutional amendment prohibiting the quartering of soldiers in civilian homes.", "answer": "<b><u>Third</u></b> Amendment to the US Constitution", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this modern-day country, researchers discovered what is considered \u201cthe</u></b> <b><u>oldest naturalistic life-sized sculpture of a human,\u201d called the Urfa Man. Berlin\u2019s Altes</u></b> <b><u>Museum contains an altar discovered by Carl Humann [[HOO-mon]] in this modern</u></b> <b><u>country at the site of ancient (+)</u> Pergamon. Near this country's city of Hisarlik, Heinrich Schliemann [[SHLEE-mon]] discovered many copper and gold artifacts belonging to (*) </b>Priam's Treasure. For ten points, name this country, where excavations have been going on for over 150 years around the ruins of Troy.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Turkey</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Until 2019, this state had only one female senator, white supremacist Rebecca</u></b> <b><u>Latimer Felton, who served for one day in 1922. In 2017 a special election in this</u></b> <b><u>state was the costliest congressional race ever. That contested seat from this state</u></b> <b><u>had belonged to the new HHS Secretary, Tom (+)</u> Price, and the loser in that election was elected to the Senate in 2020. In this state\u2019s other 2020 Senate race, the owner of the WNBA\u2019s Dream lost to the 10th (*) </b>African-American elected as US Senator. For ten points, what state elected Senators Jon Ossoff and Raphael Warnock?", "answer": "<b><u>Georgia</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this country, Imam Yahya prohibited Jews from building their houses</u></b> <b><u>higher than Muslim homes before his assassination in the Alwaziri Coup. Many Jews</u></b> <b><u>from this country were brought to Israel in Operation Magic Carpet. In 2000, the USS</u></b> <em><b><u>Cole</u></b></em><b><u> (+)</u> was bombed by al-Qaeda in a suicide attack off the coast of this country. This country's first president, Ali Abdullah (*) </b>Saleh, was assassinated by a sniper in 2017. For ten points, name this Middle Eastern country, whose ongoing civil war has involved fighting in cities like Aden and Sana'a.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Yemen</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1974, this band took a break from touring to form its own record label,</u></b> <b><u>Swan Song, signing artists such as Maggie Bell and Bad Company. Originally known as</u></b> <b><u>the New Yardbirds, this band\u2019s first three studio albums were self-titled, and their</u></b> <b><u>fourth, untitled album, sometimes referred to as (+)</u> \"Zoso,\" is one of the best-selling albums of all-time. Many of this band\u2019s songs carry historical and mythological themes, highlighted by the Norse mythology featured in 1970\u2019s (*) </b>\"Immigrant Song.\u201d For ten points, name this English rock band formed by Robert Plant and Jimmy Page.", "answer": "Led <b><u>Zeppelin</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>This holiday honors the date on which District Commander Gordon Granger</u></b> <b><u>read General Order No. 3 at Ashton Villa. Texas House Bill 1016 declared this date an</u></b> <b><u>official state holiday, while New York, Pennsylvania, and Virginia recognized it as a</u></b> <b><u>day of paid leave, following the death of (+)</u> George Floyd. John F. Callahan constructed a posthumously-released 1999 novel by Ralph Ellison (*) </b>which is titled for this holiday. For ten points, what holiday originated in Galveston and commemorates the emancipation of slaves in Texas on June 19, 1865?", "answer": "<b><u>Juneteenth</u></b> (accept <b><u>Freedom Day</u></b>, <b><u>Jubilee Day</u></b>, <b><u>Emancipation Day</u></b>, or <b><u>Liberation Day</u></b> before \u201cnovel\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The paladin Oliver de Vienne tells this man, his brother-in-law, that</u></b> <b><u>\u201cReasonableness is to be preferred to recklessness\" before succumbing to his</u></b> <b><u>wounds. The only historical mention of this otherwise literary figure is found in</u> </b><em><b><u>Vita</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Karoli Magni</u></b></em><b><u> by (+)</u> Einhard, who describes this man as a prefect of Brittany. This man mortally wounds the Saracen King Marsile during the climactic battle of (*) </b>Roncevaux Pass. For ten points, name this officer of Charlemagne who blew a horn made of an elephant tusk, the protagonist of an 11th century French \u201cSong.\u201d", "answer": "<b><u>Roland</u></b>o (accept <b><u>Orlando</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>This city includes the well-preserved cisterns of La Malga. The Baths of</u></b> <b><u>Antonius are located in this city where the physician Constantine the African was</u></b> <b><u>born. This city, the site of an exarchate and praetorian prefecture of Africa, long</u></b> <b><u>rivaled (+)</u> Utica. The first transmarine Roman colony, Colonia Junonia, was at the site of this city, where the earth was salted after Zama. Legendarily, Alyssa or Dido founded this city, which fought with (*) </b>Rome in the Punic Wars. For ten points, name this Tunisian city, home to Hannibal.", "answer": "<b><u>Carthage</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This system caused removals in Sophiatown and led to the independence of a</u></b> <b><u>state that is home to Sun City Resort. The Kairos Document was a theological</u></b> <b><u>challenge to this policy. CODESA ended this system, beginning with the National Peace</u></b> <b><u>Accord. Under this policy, the (+)</u> Trojan Horse Incident occurred, and the National Party caused the Coloured Vote Constitutional Crisis. This system caused the Soweto uprising, and (*) </b>ANC leader Nelson Mandela was jailed for opposing it. For ten points, name this South African system of institutionalized racial segregation.", "answer": "<b><u>Apartheid</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}